Finding Aid for the Barbara and Willard Morgan photographs and papers LSC.2278
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 19: Family materials, circa 1850s-1990s; 1920s-1940s
  - Subseries 19.4: Family photographic material, circa 1850s-1990s
    - Morgan - Barbara, circa 1900s-1990s; Boxes 310-311 contain small prints (up to 8x10, including supports). Boxes 331-335, 338, 343, 348-349, and 365 Medium prints (up to 16 x 20 format, including supports).
      - Barbara Morgan in her studio NYC, Lexington Ave, Scarsdale, circa 1920s-1940s; Contact prints. (Box 423)
      - Barbara Morgan standing in front of framed photograph (on auction) of Graham with flower and Hawkins (rear) in Every Soul is a Circus, circa 1980.; Small color photograph.
      - Barbara Morgan by Elsa Neumann and other photographers, Box 557 includes 4 x 5, 2-1/4" and 35mm negatives. (Box 557)
      - Barbara Morgan in turban, circa 1932-1942; 5 x 7 and smaller negatives. (Box 554)
    - Morgan - Willard, 1900s-1960s
      - Morgan family, including prints of Barbara Morgan, Willard Morgan, and Barbara and Willard Morgan together, ca. 1910s-1920s; Small photographs (4 x 6 inches and smaller, including supports) (Box 307, Folder 9)
      - Barbara, Willard, young Douglas and Lloyd Morgan, 1930s; Small prints (up to 8 x 10, including supports), of Barbara, Willard, Douglas and Lloyd. (Box 307, Folder 10)
      - Morgan family photographs and unidentified photographs, late 1800s - 1930s
        5 x 7 photographs and smaller of Morgan family, places visited or Morgan houses. Includes a photograph of elderly woman (Morgan?) in front of Buffalo, Kansas Post office, baby photographs, other relatives. Some of the photographs are self-made post cards.
      - Studio and professional portraits, and candid photographs of Willard Morgan and his family, 1900s through the 1930s; Small prints and supports (up to 8 x 10 format) (Box 310)
        Photo credits
        Most of the photographs in this box are unattributed, but some are credited to Barbara Morgan, Berenice Abbott, Alfred Eisenstaedt, and Carl M. Mydans.
      - Photographs of Willard Morgan taken by Barbara Morgan and other photographers, ca. 1940s-1960s; Small prints (up to 8 x 10, including supports). (Box 311)
      - Willard's trip with his brother, Gilbert Morgan, to Europe for the 1966 Photokina trade fair in Cologne, Germany, during which they also visited Switzerland, England, and Wales., Small photographic prints (up to 8 x 10, including supports). (Box 311)
        Slides from this trip are located in Box 322.
        Ephemera from this trip is located in Box 120, Folder 10, and Box 121, Folder 1 (Subseries 16.2).
      - 10 photographic portraits of Willard Morgan and one photograph of Willard Morgan with children, 1945, undated; (loose prints) (Box 331)
      - Willard in Pomona sports uniform, and later photograph of Willard with fellow photographer, each holding small camera, 1945, undated; 2 prints trimmed and mounted on 11 x 14 in. boards. (Box 331)
      - Willard Morgan wearing sports gear (shorts and "P" sweater, athletic shoes). Photograph by Wright Pierce, undated; Medium print trimmed and mounted on 14 x 9-1/2" board. (Box 332)
      - Willard Morgan in Bee Helmet with Barbara Morgan, 1981; Prints trimmed and mounted on 12 x 14 in. boards (3 prints). (Box 338)
      - One unidentified print of a woman holding a tiny dog, Medium print (up to 16 x 20 format, including supports) (Box 338)
      - 3 photographic portraits of Willard Morgan, by Barbara Morgan, 1945-1950; Trimmed and mounted on 12 x 15 in. boards. (Box 343)
      - Willard Morgan, Harold Harvey, and Manuel Komroff in H. H. Darkroom, 1936; Print, trimmed, mounted on 14 x 18 inch board. (Box 349)
        Photographs of Willard by Barbara Morgan from her Strobe Series can be found in Subseries 9.6. See also Subseries 18.1.
      - Willard (Herc), 5 x 7 or smaller negatives.
      - Willard Morgan by Ansel Adams and others, Box 557 includes 4 x 5, 2-1/4" and 35mm negatives. (Box 557)
      - Speedlite Portrait photographs of Willard Morgan, 1941; Negatives. (Box 607)
    - Preston, circa 1880s-1910s (Box 311, Folders 6-7)
    - Steele, circa 1880s-1890s (Box 311, Folder 9)
    - Unidentified, circa 1850s-1940s (Box 311, Folders 10-11, Box 312, Folders 1-9)
  - Subseries 19.5: Growing Americans (Chicken Movie), 1940s
    CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This subseries contains processed audiovisual materials. All requests to access audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
    This subseries contains documentation, photographic materials, and a film reel for Growing Americans (known to the family as "Chicken Movie"), a United States government short film showing the Morgan family raising chickens at their Scarsdale home. According to the documentation, the 1944 film was made as part of a food production propaganda program. It was directed by Paramount Studios' Gene Martel and produced by the Agricultural Film Unit of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs for release in South America with narration in Spanish and Portuguese. Still images in the film are credited to Barbara Morgan.
    - Growing Americans 16 mm film reel, circa 1940s
    - Photographic prints (small), contact prints and negatives, 1940s; 4 x 5 and smaller negatives and contact prints. (Box 412, Box 533, Box 534, Box 542, Box 544)
    - Documentation, 1944 (Box 412, Folder 6)
- Series 20: Publishing company materials, 1920s-1990s
  Material in this series relates to the Morgan family's involvement in the publishing industry. Willard Morgan became involved with publishing in the 1930s and founded the publishing company Morgan & Lester with his partner Henry M. Lester. They published photography texts such as Ansel Adams' Basic Photo Series as well as the Leica Manual and Graphic Graflex Photography.
  In 1956, Willard bought out Lester and then he and Barbara partnered in the business, renaming it Morgan & Morgan. Morgan & Morgan published photography texts such as Photo Lab Index and Minor White's Zone System Manual as well as later editions of Ansel Adams' Basic Photo Series and the Leica Manual.
  The company also published some of Barbara Morgan's monographs:
  (see also Series 4: Barbara Morgan photographic projects) as well as books of architectural photography, such as Mystery and Realities of the Site
  (see also Subseries 14.1: Richard Neutra).
  The Morgans' sons, Douglas and Lloyd, later became involved with the business, as well as with Morgan Press, which specialized in producing publications using Willard's typography collection and machinery.
  - Subseries 20.1: Ansel Adams materials, 1940-1989
    Materials in this subseries include correspondence, promotional material, and business records relating to Ansel Adams' relationship with Barbara and Willard Morgan, as well as their sons, Douglas and Lloyd Morgan. The Morgans collaborated with Adams on various publishing projects including Exposure Record and The Polaroid Manual.
    This subseries also includes professional material related to Adams' career, including exhibition fliers, print order forms, lecture notes, clippings, and material relating to his workshops. Correspondence includes letters written between Adams and the Morgans, as well as letters written to and from Willard representing Morgan & Morgan and Morgan & Lester, regarding the Adams books Willard was involved in publishing. Correspondence between Adams' daughter, Anne Adams, and Douglas Morgan is also present.
    Additionally, this subseries includes material related to Adams' Basic Photo Series, a series of five books published between 1948 and 1956 that aimed to introduce basic principles of photography. Materials relating to these books include correspondence, galley proofs (some in multiple copies with edits), and publications.
    - Correspondence, 1940-1969 (Box 168, Folders 1-6)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1971 (Box 169, Folders 1-6)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1976 (Box 170, Folders 1-3)
    - Notes, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 170, Folder 4)
    - Publication draft material, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 170, Folder 5)
    - Writing, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 170, Folder 6)
    - Photographic prints, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 170, Folder 7)
    - Lecture notes, 1944-1972 (Box 170, Folder 8, Box 171, Folder 1)
    - Business records, 1951-1975 (Box 171, Folder 2)
    - Clippings and publicity, 1960-1989 (Box 171, Folder 3)
    - Professional material, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 171, Folder 4)
    - Workshop material, 1960-1971 (Box 171, Folder 5)
    - Publishing agreements, circa 1970s (Box 171, Folder 6)
    - Exposure Record - 1947 edition (Box 171, Folder 7)
    - Polaroid Manual, 1963-1964 (Box 171, Folder 8)
    - Basic Photo Series - draft material, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 171, Folder 9)
    - Basic Photo Series - clippings, 1952-1958 (Box 172, Folder 1)
    - Basic Photo Series: The Print, Natural Light Photography, 1952-1966 (Box 172, Folder 2)
    - Basic Photo Series: Natural Light Photography - book jackets, 1952 (Box 172, Folder 3)
    - Basic Photo Series: Natural Light Photography - galley proofs, 1952, 1956 (Box 172, Folders 4-6, Box 173, Folders 1-6)
    - Basic Photo Series: The Print - galley proof, 1957 (Box 174, Folder 1)
    - Basic Photo Series: The Negative, 1962-1964 (Box 174, Folder 2)
    - Camera and Lens - galley proofs, 1971 (Box 175, Folders 1-3, Box 176)
  - Subseries 20.2: Mystery and Realities of the Site by Richard Neutra, 1930-1970
    This subseries includes material related to Mystery and Realities of the Site, authored by Richard Neutra and published by Morgan & Morgan in 1951. Materials include correspondence, photographs, publicity material, publication draft material, financial records, and final versions of the publication.
    Correspondence between the Morgans and Neutras primarily concerns the publication and distribution of the book, but also includes personal letters documenting various trips taken by Richard and Dione Neutra, and updates on other projects undertaken by the Morgans or Neutras. This subseries also contains correspondence, financial records, and proof material from vendors, such as the fine art printing firm Beck Engravers. Also included are approximately fifty photographic prints of Neutra structures attributed to Julius Shulman, the photographer for Mysteries and Realities of the Site.
    Other material relating to the publication include draft material such as drawings and storyboards by Richard Neutra for the design of the book's interior; photographs for the final draft and related notes; a copy of the final dust jacket with storyboards drawn by Neutra; and documentation of the planning and creation of the book jacket, including a sketch of the proposed design, copies of elements used to create a mockup, drafts of text for the cover, printed copies of the final version, one acetate negative, and photographic prints of the cover.
    - Book jacket design, 1950-1951 (Box 174, Folder 3, Box 189, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1930-1970 (Box 174, Folders 4-5)
    - First edition copies, 1951 (Box 177, Folder 1)
    - Photographic prints by Julius Shulman, circa 1950
    - Proofs, 1950-1951 (Box 177, Folders 2-3, Box 189, Folders 7-8)
    - Publicity, 1951 (Box 177, Folder 4)
    - Sketches and storyboards, circa 1950 (Box 177, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 20.3: Business records, 1920s-1990s
    Material in this subseries includes correspondence, documents concerning publication copyrights, legal contracts, financial reports, clippings, business records, publicity, work samples, letterhead, and catalogs related to the Morgans' involvement with the publishing industry. Included are materials from the different businesses in which Willard, Barbara, Douglas, and Lloyd Morgan founded and/or were involved, such as Morgan & Lester, Morgan & Morgan, and Morgan Press.
    (Related material is also located in Series 15: Willard Morgan typography files.)
    - Business material, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 177, Folder 8)
    - Business records, 1947-1981 (Box 177, Folders 6-7)
    - Contact cards, circa 1960s (Box 178, Folder 1)
    - Copyright documents, 1935-1994 (Box 178, Folders 2-3)
    - Correspondence, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 178, Folders 4-6)
    - Correspondence - Morgan Christmas cards, circa 1920s-1980s (Box 178, Folder 7)
    - Morgan Archive - materials and publications, circa 1990s (Box 179, Folders 1-3)
      Includes articles and reprints of articles by and about Barbara Morgan.
    - Morgan & Morgan - catalogs, 1951-1989 (Box 179, Folder 4)
    - Morgan & Morgan Photo Game - research material, project notes, circa 1940s (Box 179, Folder 5)
    - Morgan Press - catalogs, circa 1960s (Box 179, Folder 6)
    - Newhall, Nancy and Beaumont - correspondence and notes, 1942-1990 (Box 179, Folder 7)
    - Notes, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 179, Folder 8)
    - Photographic prints, circa 1960s (Box 180, Folder 1)
    - Photographic prints - unidentified, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 180, Folder 2)
    - Publication and print-related exhibitions, events, collection catalogs, ephemera, circa 1960s (Box 180, Folder 3)
    - Publicity and clippings, 1940s-1970s (Box 180, Folders 4-6)
    - Supplementary material, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 180, Folder 7)
    - Work samples, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 180, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 20.4: Publications, 1928-1989
    Material in this subseries includes correspondence, draft material, galley proofs, photographs, notes, and research material relating to books published by Morgan & Morgan, Morgan & Lester, and Morgan Press. Published versions of books, including Graphic Graflex, Stereo Realist Manual, the Leica Manual, Photo-Lab-Index, and Miniature Camera Work are represented in this subseries. Some publications are inscribed by the Morgans while others contain multiple editions. This subseries also contains correspondence and notes related to unpublished works and publication ideas.
    Some related material is located in Series 12: Willard Morgan photography career.
    - Block, Lou - correspondence, photographs, 1961 (Box 184, Folder 3)
    - Correct Exposure in Photography - first edition, 1944 (Box 184, Folder 4)
    - Freedomland - issues, publicity, 1960-1964 (Box 189, Folders 9-10)
    - Graphic Graflex - notes, publishing material, correspondence, photographs, 1954-1970s (Box 181, Folders 1-7)
    - Lange, Dorothea - correspondence, 1973 (Box 184, Folder 8)
    - Leica Manual - supplementary booklets, editions, publication material, research material, 1928-1960s (Box 182, Folders 1-5)
    - Leica Manual - business records and correspondence, 1956 (Box 183, Folder 1)
    - Photo Lab Index, 1943-1989 (Box 185, Box 186)
    - Photo Lab Index - drafts and publicity, circa 1960s (Box 184, Folder 5)
    - To Lighten My House by Alastair Reid - correspondence, drafts, business records, 1953-1965 (Box 184, Folder 6)
    - White, Minor publications - business records, correspondence, drafts, proofs, research material, 1950s-1970s (Box 183, Folders 2-12)
      Materials related to the Zone System Manual, Exposure to the Zone System, The Way of Photography, and Care of Photographs.
    - White, Minor - Visualization Manual - proofs and correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 184, Folders 1-2)
    - Publication ideas - notes, correspondence, clippings, circa 1930s-1970s (Box 184, Folder 9)
    - Publication ideas - Spiegel, Motoko Ikeda: correspondence, clippings, research, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 184, Folder 10)
    - Published volumes, 1940s-1970s (Box 187, Box 226, Box 227, Box 228, Box 229)
      An incomplete set of the following titles: Ansel Adams' Basic Photo series and Polaroid Manual, Minor White's Zone System Manual, plus Foundry Type, Graphic Graflex Photography, Illustrated Catalog of Photographic Equipments and Materials for Amateurs, Leica Manual, Miniature Camera Work, Photo Dictionary, Photo Quiz, Stereo Realist Manual, and TV and Film Production Data Book.
    - Unidentified publications, circa 1950s (Box 184, Folder 7)
- Series 21: Artifacts and audiovisual materials, 1920s-1980s
  Artifacts include two Leica cameras with cases, one Zeiss camera with case, one Exakta camera with case, and two Graphlex cameras. Film holders, film canisters, and various other photography tools are also present. Audiovisual materials include film, video, and audio.
  CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO and AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audio and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email AskLSC@library.ucla.edu.
  - Barbara Morgan art portfolios (emptied), 1930, undated (Box 196, Folder 4, Box 215, Folder 2, Box 396, Folder 3)
  - Barbara Morgan wood blocks, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 249, Box 250, Box 251, Box 252, Box 253, Box 254)
    Wood blocks made and used by Barbara Morgan to make prints related to Series 10: Barbara Morgan drawings, paintings, and prints, circa 1900s-1960s, Subseries 10.3: Prints, circa 1900s-1960s. Some carved on both sides.
    Also includes two small wood blocks with metal plates and no artist attribution.
  - Copyright rubber stamps with metal holder, 1930s-1980s (Box 219)
  - Camera equipment and photography tools, circa 1920s-1950s
    Includes Barbara and Willard Morgan's cameras and related photography accessories.
    - Zeiss Ikon camera (brown leather case, broken strap) (Box 416)
    - Exakta VX Ihagee Dresden camera; black Ernest Leitz Elmar 1:3.5 F=50mm with lens cap (no case) (Box 416)
    - Leica B. R. P. Ernst Leitz Wetslav no. 328718 Summtar f=5cm 1:2 no.505419 (brown leather case, no strap) (Box 416)
    - Leitz Wetxlar black camera case (Box 416)
    - Graflex Sisto Gum Camera (Box 417)
    - Super Graphic Graflex 45 with handbook (Box 417)
    - Metal camera carrying case (Box 418)
    - 2 Graflex film holders (Box 418)
    - 221 Graflex film holders (4 x 5) (Box 418)
    - Graflex Sisto Gum Camera (Box 418)
    - 1 Model 2 Graphic film pack adapter (Box 418)
    - 2 Graflex holders (Box 418)
    - Bulbs, spools, lenses, booklets, and other tools (Box 453)
  - Stereo Realist viewer, glass slides, and supplies, circa 1950s (Box 413, Box 414, Box 415)
    These glass slide materials relate to the book published by Morgan & Lester in 1954, Stereo Realist Manual. In addition to the red button Stereo Realist viewer, these materials also include a single slide viewer labeled with Barbara Morgan's name.
  - Audiovisual materials
    - 8 VHS, 8 U-Matics, 4 DVDs, and 4 audio tapes (Box 199)
    - 27 audiocassettes, 13 VHS, 2 audio tapes, 2 wire recordings, and 1 U-Matic (Box 200)
    - 8 lacquer disc(s) (Box 596)